快点 不能再让人们等太久了
Quick,We can't hold them back much longer.
赶紧
Hurry
快!
Come on!
Quick!
快点!
Faster!
开门 快 快!
Open the doors, Come on, quickly!
绞死他 该死的人渣!
String him up, the burning scum!
要让他也尝尝我妹妹受的痛苦!
Let him suffer like my sister suffered!
交给我们来处置他!
Give him to the people!
你将永受火刑的诅咒!
May you burn in the eternal fires of damnation!
把判决结果念了
Just read them the sentence.
你杀了我妹妹 你必须付出代价!
You killed my sister! You'll pay, you will!
法庭判决结果如下:
The sentence of the court
两天之后
is that in two days hence
香水制造熟练工 让·巴蒂斯特·格雷诺耶
the perfumer journeyman Jean Baptiste Grenouille
将被绑在一个木十字架上
shall be bound to a wooden cross
面朝天空
with his face raised toward heaven,
由行刑者用铁棍活活猛击十二下
And whilst still alive be dealt twelve blows with an iron rod
使其臂 肩 髋 腿部关节全部碎裂
breaking the joints of his arms, his shoulders, his hips, his legs,
并钉在十字架上示众 一直到死
He shall then be raised up to hang until dead
并禁止行刑官使用通常的人道做法
and all customary acts of mercy
要使其生不如死
are expressly forbidden the executioner!
十八世纪法国曾出现过这么一个人
In 18th. Century France,there lived a man
他天赋异禀 又恶名昭彰
who was one of the most gifted and notorious personages of his time.
他名叫让·巴蒂斯特·格雷诺耶
His name was Jean Baptiste Grenouille
如果他的名字现今已经被人遗忘
and if his name has been forgotten today
只因他野心的仅仅局限于
it is for the sole reason that his entire ambition
在历史完全不曾留下痕迹的领域
was restricted to a domain that leaves no trace in history
即转瞬即逝的气味王国
To the fleeting realm of scent
香水: 一个谋杀犯的故事
Perfume: The Story Of A Murderer
我们所要讲述的这个时代里 各城市中始终弥漫着
In the period of which we speak, there reigned in the cities a stench
我们现代人难以想象的臭气
barely conceivable to us modern men and women,
当然 最秽臭的要数巴黎
Naturally, the stench was foulest in Paris
因为巴黎是欧洲最大的城市
for Paris was the largest city in Europe,
而在巴黎市内最令人作呕的恶臭又来自鱼贩集市
And nowhere in Paris was that stench more profoundly repugnant than in the city is fish market,
先就这些 我再拿个箱子来
Here we are, I'll get another box
而就在这整个王国最腐臭的地方
It was here, then, on the most putrid spot in the whole kingdom
让·巴蒂斯特·格雷诺耶在1738年7月17日这天出世了
that Jean Baptiste Grenouille was born on the 17th of July, 1738.
这是他母亲生的第五胎
It was his mother is fifth birth
每次都在这鱼摊旁完成
She id delivered them all here under her fish stand
每次都是死胎或半死胎
and all had been stillbirths, or semi. Stillbirths
你没事吧?
You all right?
到了晚上 这堆乱糟糟的东西
And by evening the whole mess had been shoveled away
就和鱼肠之类一起 统统铲进河里
with the fish guts into the river
今天这次本该也是如此
It would be much the same today
但让·巴蒂斯特的选择却有所不同
but then, Jean Baptiste chose differently,
什么声音?
What's that noise?
- 是个婴儿  - 出了什么事?
- It's a baby,  - What's going on here?
一个新生儿
It's a newborn
他妈妈在哪?
Where's its mother?
刚还在这儿的
She was just here
她居然想弄死他! 是她自己的孩子啊!
She tried to kill it. Her own child.
她居然想弄死她的婴儿
She tried to kill her baby!
那儿! 她在那儿!
There! There she is!
站住! 给我站住!
Stop! Stop where you are!
杀人犯!
Murderer!
如此这般 格雷诺耶口中发出的第一声哭喊
Thus, the first sound to escape Grenouilleis lips
把他的母亲送上了绞刑台
sent his motherto the gallows
而让·巴蒂斯特则由官方授权托付给了
and Jean Baptiste, by official order
加拉尔夫人的育婴所
to the orphanage of Madame Gaillard,
今天几个?
How many today?
四个 呃 现在只剩三个半了
Four, Well, three and a half,
又是老样子 死样活气的
As usual, more dead than alive,
行了 收钱签字完事吧
Just take the money and sign,
让让
Make room
怎么让?
Where?
让啊!
Move!
快让
Go on, now
他死了吗?
Is it dead?
我才不要他待在我床上
That's not staying in my bed
我们干掉他算了
Let's throw it out, then
要是他哭起来怎么办?
What if it screams?
一个小毛孩罢了
Let's just kill it
用力! 按!
Harder! Push!
你们干什么?
What are you doing?!
对加拉尔夫人来说格雷诺耶和别人一样都不过是收入来源
For Mme Gaillard, Grenouille was a source of income just like any other
孩子们却敏锐地察觉到
The children, however, sensed at once
这个婴孩不比寻常
that there was something different about him
让·巴蒂斯特直到五岁还不会说话
By the age of five, Jean Baptiste still could not talk,
但他却有着与生俱来的异禀天赋
But he had been born with a talent that made him unique among mankind,
倒不是说其它孩子有多痛恨他
It was not that the other children hated him
而是他让他们紧张不安
they felt unnerved by him
渐渐地 他开始明白这种对气味奇异的天赋
Increasingly he became aware that his phenomenal sense of smell
归他所有 唯他独有
was a gift that had been given to him, and him alone
当让·巴蒂斯特最终开口学习说话的时候
When Jean Baptiste did finally learn to speak
他很快就发现自己积累的嗅觉体验
he soon found that everyday language proved inadequate
仅靠日常词语根本不能描述
for all the olfactory experiences accumulating within himself
木头
Wood
干的木头
Warm wood
草
Grass
湿的草
Wet grass
石头
Stones
干的石头
Warm stones
水
Water
冰冷的水
Cold water
青蛙
Frog
湿的石头
Wet stones
大的 湿的青蛙…石头
Big, wet frog stones
什么东西
Something
什么东西 什么
something, something
他十三岁时 加拉尔夫人的地方不够给他住了
By the age of 13, Madame Gaillard no longer had room forJean Baptiste
于是决定把他卖掉
and therefore decided to sell him
快走
Come on
十法郎
Ten francs
第一次闻到这人周围环绕的臭气
From his first breath of the odor enveloping this man
七法郎 一分也不多
Seven, and not one sou more
格雷诺耶就知道在格里马制革铺
Grenouille knew that his life in Grimalis tannery
他的性命值什么价全由他能干多少活而定
would be won'th precisely as much as the work he could accomplish,
走
Come on
加拉尔夫人可就不太走运了
Unfortunately for Madame Gaillard
拿着!
Take it!
做了场送命的交易
The bargain was short. Lived
在制革铺里可预计的生命周期仅有五年
Life expectancy in the tannery was a mere five years
但让·巴蒂斯特的生命力却有如病菌一样顽强
but Jean Baptiste proved to be as tough as a resilient bacterium
他适应了新的命运 温顺又勤劳 俨然工人楷模
He adjusted to his new fate and became a paragon of docility and diligence
不分寒暑的每天勤奋劳作十五 六个小时
Slaved 15, 16 hours a day,summer and winter
渐渐地 他开始意识到制革铺之外的世界
Gradually he became aware of a world beyond the tannery
那里有未经探索的气味乌托邦正静候他前往探寻
where a Utopia of unexplored smells lay in store for him
格雷诺耶!
Grenouille!
跟我们来 我带你去镇上送货
Come with us,I'm taking you to town for delivery
让·巴蒂斯特·格雷诺耶成功了
Jean Baptiste Grenouille had triumphed
他存活了下来
He was alive
且终于如鱼得水
and at last he was in his element
对气味他并不加以抉择
He was not choosy
也不挑拣世俗眼光所认同的香臭
He did not differentiate between what are commonly considered to be good smells from bad
至少 目前还不曾
at least not yet
他很贪婪
He was very greedy
想把这个世界所提供的气味统统占为己有
The goal was to possess everything the world had to offer in the way of odors
唯一的标准是这些气味应该是以前未知的
His only condition being,that they were new ones
千千万万种气味融成无形的稀粥
Thousands upon thousands of odors formed an invisible gruel
他将其分解成最细微的分子与部分
which he dissected into its smallest and most remote parts and pieces
来买今晚圣母院烟火晚会的旗子啊
Buy your pennant here fortonight's fireworks at Notre Dame
格雷诺耶!
Grenouille!
过来!
Come on!
快他妈的过来!
Get your ass over here!
他下周要两打皮子 你能有吗?
He needs two dozen skins by next week, Can you do that?
- 嗯 嗯  - 跟我来
- Yeah, Yeah  - come with me
它叫什么名字?
What is it called?
爱神与赛琪 夫人
Amor and Psyche, madame
我的最新成果
My latest creation
我能试试吗?
May I try it?
请让我来 小姐
If you'll allow me, mademoiselle
我的天那!
Sheer heaven!
佩利西埃先生 您可真是位技艺家
Monsieur Pelissier, you are truly an artiste
请拿着吧 我这里还多着呢
Please, take them, I've got fartoo many
你想要什么?
What do you want?
要买些吗?
Want to buy some?
一苏尔两只
Two for a sou
请勿靠近!
Stand clear!
下次再跑远了的话 我就杀了你!
Next time you run off like that,I'll kill you!
当晚他无法入眠
That night, he could not sleep
那女孩醉人的气息突然让他清醒地意识到
The intoxicating power of the girl's scent suddenly made it clear to him
他的生命为什么如此顽强 狂野
why he'd come to his own life so tenaciously, so savagely
他悲惨的生活有了意义与目标也有了更高的使命
The meaning and purpose of his miserable existence had a higher destiny
他必须学会如何保藏气味
He would learn how to preserve scent
这样 他才再也不会遗失这种超凡的美
so that never again would he lose such sublime beauty
当年在巴黎 至少有一打的香水制造者
There were about a dozen perfumers in Paris in those days
其中有一位曾负盛名的香水制造者意大利人吉赛佩·巴尔迪尼
One of them, the once. Celebrated Italian perfumer, Giuseppe Baldini
三十多年前 他刚来到巴黎的时候
had set up shop in the center of the bridge called the Pont au...
在兑换桥的正中开了一间店铺
...Change on his arrival in Paris over thirty years ago
当然 在他年轻时
To be sure, at one time in his youth
的确也设计出来过几款高明的香水并由此赚得了他如今的全副身家
Baldini had created several truly great perfumes, to which he owed his fortune
但如今 巴尔迪尼已经落伍了 不时新了
But now Baldini was out of touch, out of fashion
他整日在店铺中苦苦守候 但顾客们已不复再来
and spent his days waiting for customers that no longer came
谢尼埃 你来了!
Chnier! There you are!
巴尔迪尼先生
Monsieur Baldini
把假发戴上
Put on your wig
把你的假发戴上!
Put on your wig!
你要出门?
You going out?
我现在要回书房独处几个小时
I wish to retire to my study for a few hours
不希望任何人打搅
and do not want to be disturbed under any circumstances
你要设计新香水吗 巴尔迪尼先生?
Will you be creating a new perfume, Monsieur Baldini?
没错 给维拉蒙特伯爵的
Correct, For Count Verhamont
他要一种 像那个像…
He has asked for something like
我记得他说的是叫什么…"爱神与赛琪"的香水吧?
I think he said it was called Amor and Psyche
就是那个圣安德烈艺术大街的骗子…
from that swindler in the Rue Saint Andre des Arts
佩利西埃?
Pelissier?
佩利西埃 就是他
Pelissier, that's him
哈! 爱神与赛琪
Amor and Psyche
- 你听说过吗?  - 嗯 当然
- Do you know it?  - Oh, yes.
现在到处都能闻到这种香水 先生
You can smell it everywhere these days, monsieur
满大街都是
On every street corner
事实上 我给您买了一瓶样品
In fact, I just purchased you a sample
如果您想试闻一下的话
In case you wanted to test it
你怎么会认为我有兴趣试这个?
What on earth makes you think I'd be interested in testing it?
您说得对 这没什么特别
You're right, It's nothing special
老实说 这气味挺庸常的
Actually,it's a very common scent
我相信 前调里用了不少青柠油
I believe the head chord contains lime oil
真的?
Really?
中调呢?
And the heart chord?
我猜是橙花香精
Orange blossom, I believe
后调也许是麝猫香酊 但我不敢肯定
And civet in the base chord, but, you know, I cannot say for sure
无所谓了 管那个半瓶醋往他的香水里掺什么呢!
Well, I couldn't care less what that bungler Pelissier slops into his perfumes
的确如此 先生
Naturally not, monsieur
我为维拉蒙特伯爵设计的东西
And I am thinking of creating something for Count Verhamont
肯定能引起真正的轰动
that will cause a veritable sensation
那是一定的 巴尔迪尼先生
I'm sure it will, Monsieur Baldini
店里的事你来照顾 谢尼埃 别让任何人打扰我
Take charge of the shop, Chnier, and don't let anyone come near me
灵感需要静谧安宁
Inspiration requires peace and tranquility
还需要别的什么吗?
Is there anything else you need?
灵感吧 也许
Inspiration, perhaps
啊 我的先生
Ah, my Giuseppe
您依然是伟大的香水制作者巴尔迪尼
You are still the great perfumer Baldini
妙极了
Wonderful
他又成功了
He did it again
青柠油 果然
Lime oil. Yes, indeed
橙花香精 没错
Orange blossom to be sure
一缕丁香 大概
And a hint of cloves, perhaps
不 也可能是肉桂
No, Or could be cinnamon?
气味走了
It's gone
是肉桂
Cinnamon
不是肉桂
It's not cinnamon
丁香?
Cloves?
不对
No
麝香?
Musk?
不对
No
是谁?
Who's there?
我是从格里马的制革铺来
I'm from Grimal's tannery
送来了您订购的山羊皮
I've brought the goat skins you ordered
跟我来
Follow me
这边
This way
那里
There
就放那里
Lay them there
跟你主人说 皮子不错
Tell your masterthat the skins are fine
我过两天会顺路去付账
I'll come by in the next few days and pay for them
是的 先生
Yes, monsieur
您是想让这皮子变得好闻 对吧?
You want to make this leather smell good, don't you?
的确如此 会变好闻的
Why, of course, And so it shall,
用佩利西埃的"爱神与赛琪"香水?
With Amor and Psyche by Pelissier?
我会用别家做的香水? 你哪来的这种荒谬想法?
Whatever gave you the absurd idea? I would use someone else's perfume?
你全身都是这味道
It's all over you
你的额头 鼻子 手
It's on your forehead, your nose, your hands
这个"爱神与赛琪"不好 师傅
It's bad, Amor and Psyche is, master
迷迭香太多 还有这个 这个也太多
There's too much rosemary in it and too much of that and that
佛手柑和广藿香?
Bergamotand patchouli?
广藿香
Patchouli
广藿香 广藿香
Patchouli, patchouli
还有什么?
What else?
这些
That and that
还有这些
橙花
Orange blossom
青柠
lime
- 麝香  - 迷迭香
- musk  - Rosemary
还有丁香
and cloves
还有这个
And this
安息香?
Storax?
这也在里面
That's in it, too
安息香?
Storax?
- 安息香?  - 安息香
- Storax?  - Storax
年轻人 看起来你鼻子还挺灵,但是…
You have, it appears, a fine nose, young man, But a
我的鼻子能分辨世上所有的气味
My nose knows all the smells in the world
是巴黎最灵的 我只是不知道名称
It's the best nose in Paris, only I don't know the names
但我可以学 统统学会…
I need to learn the names, learn them all
住嘴! 你别打断我说话!
You don't interrupt me when I'm speaking
你这个人太无礼 太狂妄!
You are both impertinent and insolent!
连我都不能分辨所有的气味!
Even I don't know every scent!
我当然早就知道"爱神与赛琪"的内容组成
I've, of course, known for some time the ingredients of Amor and Psyche
只要有个灵敏的鼻子就行 别无其他
But all it needs to find that out is a passably fine nose, nothing else
但只有凭真正的香水专家的技艺
But it needs the craft of a true perfumer
才能弄清楚具体的配方
to detect the exact formula
用什么香调 什么原料及精确的用量
Which notes, which chords, and in what precise measurements
你能告诉我"爱神与赛琪"的配方是什么吗?
Could you tell me the exact formula of Amor and Psyche?
巴黎最灵的鼻子!
Best Nose In Paris!
说话啊!
Speak up!
你看 不行了吧 行吗? 我告诉你
You see, you can't, can you? And I'll tell you why.
因为有点天赋那不算什么
Because talent means next to nothing
多年经验 谦谨态度 辛勤工作 那才决定了一切
while experience acquired in humility and hard work means everything
我不知道"配方"是什么意思
I don't know what a formula is
但我现在就可以帮你把"爱神与赛琪"做出来
but I can make Amor and Psyche for you now
你以为我会让你在我的实验室里胡闹?
And you think I'd just let you slop around in my laboratory
用价值连城的香精油胡闹? 就凭你?
with essential oils that are won't a fortune? You?
嗯
Yes
听好了
Now, pay attention!
你叫什么名字来着?
What is your name, anyway?
让·巴蒂斯特·格雷诺耶
Jean Baptiste Grenouille
好吧 让·巴蒂斯特·格雷诺耶
Very well, Jean Baptiste Grenouille
我给你个机会 让你证明你说的话
You shall have the opportunity now, this very moment, to prove your assertion
你会败得很惨
Your grandiose failure will also be an opportunity for you
但这也是让你学习谦虚美德的一个机会
to learn the virtue of humility
你想让我做多少?
How much do you want me to make?
多少什么?
How much of what?
爱神与赛琪 你想要多少?
How much Amor and Psyche do you want?
要把这个烧瓶装满吗?
Shall I fill this flask?
别! 你休想!
No! You shall not!
把这个装满吧
You may fill this one
是的 师傅
Yes, master
但是 巴尔迪尼先生
But, Master Baldini?
您得让我照我自己的法子来
You must let me do it in my own way
随你便吧
As you please
别!
No!
小心摔了 那可是纯酒精!
Don't drop that! That's pure alcohol!
你想把整个房子都烧了吗?
You want to blow up the entire building?
你得先用量筒
You have to measure it first
够了! 给我停下! 停下!
Stop! Stop it! That's enough!
你屁也不懂!
You know nothing!
得先混合精油 然后才添进酒精
Essential oils are always to be mixed first, then the alcohol added
还有 香水哪能那样乱摇的!
And never, ever is perfume to be shaken like that!
我真是昏了头 居然听信了你的胡说八道!
I must have been insane to listen to your asinine gibberish!
做好了
It's all done
真的是爱神与赛琪
This is Amor and Psyche
这香水不好 师傅
But it's not a good perfume, master
如果您允许我再来一次的话 师傅 我可以改进它
If you let me again, master, I'll make it more better
这香水就相当好了
Now it's a really good perfume
您不想闻一下吗 师傅?
Don't you want to smell it, master?
现在没心情 我有别的事要操心 你走吧
I'm not in the mood to test it now, I have other things on my mind, Go now
- 但是师傅  - 快走吧!
- But, master.  - Go! Now!
让我在您这儿工作吧 师傅 行吗?
Can I come to work for you, master? Can I?
我得仔细考虑一下
Let me think about it
师傅!
Master!
我必须学会怎样保存气味!
I have to learn how to keep smell!
什么?
What?
你能教我吗?
Can you teach me that?
我得想想 你走吧
I shall have to think about it, Now, go
我爱你
I love you
我给你五十法郎 把他买下
I'll give you 50 francs for him
我说什么了? 用尽你全身的力气去推!
What have I said? Put your measly weight behind it and push!
- 继续推!  - 快啊 贱骨头!
- Keep pulling!  - Come on, you heap of bones!
推! 用力推!
Push! Push hard!
格雷诺耶!
Grenouille!
格里马的交易对三方人士都影响重大
Grimal's transaction had a profound effect on all three parties
嘿 小心!
Hey, watch out!
对他自己 也殊非轻忽
Not least upon Monsieur Grimal himself
至于巴尔迪尼
As for Giuseppe Baldini
他本渐衰落的商店 竟奇迹般地复苏了
the acquisition of Grenouille miraculously transformed his dwindling business
甚至超越了当年全盛时期的景况
even surpassing its former glory
而对让·巴蒂斯特而言
While at last, for Jean Baptiste
香水制作的神秘工艺也终于在他面前呈现
the mysterious secrets of the perfumer's craft began to unfold
他是个天才!
He's a genius!
真是太好了!
It's magnificent!
仔细听着我的话
Now, pay careful attention to what I tell you
正如和弦音一样 香水的调子也包含着四种要素或原料
Just like a musical chord, a perfume chord contains four essences
都经过精心选择 以达到和谐统一
or notes, carefully selected for their harmonic affinity
每种香水有三调
Each perfume contains three chords:
前调 中调 和后调 总体有十二种香料
The head, the heart and the base, necessitating twelve notes in all
前调是最初的体验
The head chord contains the first impression
停留几分钟然后中调步入
lasting a few minutes before giving way to the heart chord
那是香水的主题 会停留几个小时
the theme of the perfume, lasting several hours
末了是后调
Finally, the base chord
香水的余韵会停留几天
the trail of the perfume, lasting several days
记住 古埃及人相信
Mind you, the ancient Egyptians believed
要制造出真正新颖的香水
that one can only create a truly original perfume
还必须外加一种香料
by adding an extra note, one final essence
它要能脱颖而出 臣服其它的味道
that will ring out and dominate the others
传说在一位法老的坟墓中曾发掘出一个双耳陶瓶
Legend has it that an amphora was once found in a pharaoh's tomb
打开之后 其中释放香水芳香
and when it was opened a perfume was released
千载之后依然萦绕不散
After all those thousands of years,
那芬郁气息细腻而又强烈
a perfume of such subtle beauty and yet such power
一时间 地球上所有人都以为自己进入了天堂
that for one single moment every person on earth believed they were in paradise
其中十二中要素都被分辨了出来
Twelve essences could be identified
但最后第十三种 最重要的那种
but the 13th, the vital one
却永远无从判断
could never be determined
为什么?
Why not?
为什么? 什么为什么?
Why not? What do you mean, why not?
那是传说啊 笨蛋!
Because it's a legend, numbskull!
什么叫"传说"?
What's a legend?
算了吧
Never mind
让·巴蒂斯特 让·巴蒂斯特?
Jean Baptiste, Jean Baptiste?
怎么了?
What's the matter?
师傅 我得学会怎么捕捉气味
Master, I have to learn how to capture scent
你在说什么?
What are you talking about?
我得学会怎么捕捉气味然后永远拥有它
I have to learn how to capture scent and reprise it forever
你是说 保藏
You mean, preserve
你得要教我
You have to teach me that
好的 冷静 我的孩子
All right, Calm down, my boy
冷静
Calm down
我们有工作要做的
We have work to do
生命的精魂就在于气味
The soul of beings is their scent
这话是您说的 师傅
You said that, master
是吗?
Did I?
您要多少香水我都可以做
I will make you as many perfumes as you want
但您必须教会我怎么捕捉万物的气味
but you have to teach me how to capture the smell of all things
行吗?
Can you do that?
唔 当然了
Well, naturally
那把您知道的都教给我吧
Then teach me everything you know
我会给您制作世上最好的香水
and I'll make you the best perfume in the whole world
小心
Mind yourselves
想想看啊 让·巴蒂斯特
Imagine, Jean Baptiste
上万朵玫瑰才凝成一盎司的精油
ten thousand roses to produce one single ounce of essential oil
就是这些了
That's the last of them
保持空气流动 别把底下的花朵闷坏了
Now, keep the air flowing or the bottom petals will begin to stew
我去把炉子架起来 可别碰伤了它们
while I set up the alembic, And take care not to damage them
它们死去时 芳香必须丝毫无损
We have to let them go to their deaths with their scent intact
很好
Perfect
帮我把这盖子架上
Now, help me with the Moor's head
温度至关重要
Temperature is vital
水银达到刻度这里的时候热度就刚刚好
When the quicksilver is here, the heat is precisely correct
精油缓缓由此上升
and the oil will gradually rise
这机制可不同寻常 是我自己设计的
Note that this mechanism is a remarkable invention of my own devising
你能看到抽上来的冷水通过这里
You will observe how cold water is pumped through here
让精油就在这部分冷凝
allowing the essence to condense here
最终在此积聚
until it finally, appears, here
当然 在格拉斯的山野上
Of course, out on the hillside above Grasse
我们只用纯净的新鲜空气就行了
we had only to bellow pure, fresh air
啊 格拉斯
Ah, Grasse
多好的镇子啊
What a town
芬芳的古城 香水的宝地
The Rome of scents, The Promised Land of perfume
没在那神圣的地方历练过的人
No man can rightly call himself a perfumer
就不配自称香水制造者
unless he has proved his won't in that hallowed place
不必担心 一直都这样
Not to worry, Happens all the time
敬格拉斯一杯
To Grasse
师傅 看
Master, Look
玫瑰的精魂
The very soul of the rose
让·巴蒂斯特
Jean Baptiste
怎么了?
What's wrong?
让·巴蒂斯特
Jean Baptiste
你都做了些什么啊?
What have you done?
你说谎
You lied
什么?
What?
你骗我
You lied to me
你敢这样跟我说话?
How dare you talk to me like that
你说我可以捕捉所有东西的气味
You said I could capture the scent of anything
是可以的啊
And so you can
你闻闻看 这是什么?
What do you smell?
这是什么?
什么也没有
Nothing
你指望它闻起来什么味道?
What were you expecting to smell?
玻璃味
Glass
可是玻璃没有味道
But glass doesn't smell
当然有了 这是什么?
Course it does, What's this?
我什么也闻不出来
I don't smell a thing
应该是铜的味道!
It should smell like copper!
够了!
Enough!
你想蒸馏铜的味道?
You were trying to distill the smell of copper?
铁 玻璃 铜?
Iron? Glass? Copper?
你还试了什么?
What else did you try?
不!
No!
你是不是疯了? !
Have you gone completely insane?!
你说要我实验的
You told me I had to experiment
实验?
Experiment?
实验?  你别拿猫啊
Experiment?! But not with the cat
你这人怎么这样? !
What kind of a human being are you?
什么都不懂吗?!
Don't you know anything?!
猫的味道是不可能蒸馏出来的
You can no more distill the scent of a cat
正如你同我的味道一样 不行的
than you can distill the scent of you or me
不行吗?
I can't?
当然不行
Of course not!
- 他已经病入膏肓了  - 什么?
- He is in stadio ultimo,  - What?
- 他快死了  - 难道没有解救的方法吗?
- He's dying,  - Is there nothing you can do?
- 恐怕没有  - 不行!
- I fear not  - No
- 他不能死啊  - 诊金50法郎
- He cannot die,  - Well, my fee is 50 francs
50法郎? 有没有搞错! 你甚至都没诊断出他得了什么病!
50 francs?! You charlatan! You can't even name the disease!
让·巴蒂斯特 别这样对待我 请别因我而死
You cannot do this to me, Please, don't die on me
别死 别现在死啊
Not now, Not yet
除了蒸馏之外还有别的办法能保存事物的气味吗?
Is there any other way to preserve smell besides distill it?
让·巴蒂斯特?
Jean Baptiste?
有吗 师傅?
Is there, master?
有 我想是有办法的
Well, yes, I believe there is
怎样?
What is it?
这种神秘的技艺 叫做油脂离析法
It is known as the mysterious art of enfleurage
您能教我吗?
Can you teach me?
连我都不知道其中秘密啊
Not even I am intimate with its secrets
那我能去格拉斯学到吗?
But could I learn it in Grasse?
唔
Well
能吗?
Could I?
当然是在格拉斯 还能在哪呢?
Where else but in Grasse?
一星期内 格雷诺耶就完全康复了
Within a week Grenouille was well again
但如果想去格拉斯找工作
but in order to travel to Grasse and find a job
他需要一份学徒升熟练工的满师证书
he needed a journey mars papers
巴尔迪尼答应给他开一份文书
Baldini agreed to provide them
前提是格雷诺耶为他留下
on condition that Grenouille left him not less
不少于一百种新香水的配方
than one hundred formulas for new perfumes
格雷诺耶并不介怀 要一千种配方都无所谓
Grenouille did not mind, He could have given him a thousand
格雷诺耶离去的那早 巴尔迪尼心情颇为愉快
The morning of Grenouilleis departure, Baldini was pleased
他觉得多年来的辛勤工作总算有了回报
At last, he felt rewarded for his many years of hard work
这是他一生记忆中最快乐的一天
He could not remember a happier day
他满心欢喜地回去睡觉
Deeply satisfied, he went back to sleep
从此便长眠不醒
and awoke no more in this life
格雷诺耶每离城市远一些 他就越觉快乐
With every step Grenouille took away from the city, the happier he felt
周围的空气变得清晰 纯净 明洁
The air above him grew clearer, purer, cleaner
他终于得以自由呼吸
and at last he was able to breathe freely
去格拉斯有两条路
There were two ways to reach Grasse
第一条路蜿蜒穿过村落
The first followed the winding roads through the villages
第二条路则直接翻过山岭 下达普罗旺斯
while the second lead straight across the hills and mountains, down into Provence
选择显而易见
The choice was quite easy
他的鼻子指引他远离人烟
Thus his nose led him ever higher, ever further from mankind
愈高愈远 愈孤寂荒凉 寂寞有如磁极 引领他前往顶峰
ever more towards the magnetic, pole of the greatest possible solitude
一时间 格雷诺耶简直不相信他找到了一处
Grenouille needed a moment to believe that he had actually found a spot on earth
几乎全无气味的地方
where scent was almost absent
周围铺展着的只有死寂的石头的宁静气息
Spread all around lay nothing but the tranquil scent of dead stone
这是片神圣的地方
There was something sacred about this place
没有外界事物的侵扰
No longer distracted by anything external
他终于可以沐浴在自我之中
he was finally able to bask in his own existence
感觉极其美妙
and found it splendid
如此过了一阵 他几乎忘了自己的野心和执念
After a while, he almost forgot his plans and obsessions
差点也就全然放弃了
and, indeed, might have done so altogether
喂?
Hello?
他的衣服间有千百种气味
There were a thousand smells in his clothes
沙 石 苔藓
The smell of sand, stone, moss
甚至几周前吃的香肠
Even the smell of the sausage he'd eaten weeks ago
只差一种气味
Only one smell was not there
他自己的
His own
有生之来
For the first time in his life
格雷诺耶初次意识到他没有自己的气味
Grenouille realized that he had no smell of his own
他一生对他人都无足轻重
He realized that all his life he had been a nobody to everyone
他怕自我被忽视 被湮没
What he now felt was the fear of his own oblivion
仿佛他不复存在
It was as though he did not exist
第二天晨曦初现 格雷诺耶就有了新的计划
By the first light of next morning, Grenouille had a new plan
他必须继续踏上格拉斯的行旅
He must continue his journey to Grasse
在那里他不仅要告诉这世界他的存在
There he would teach the world not only that he existed, that he was someone
他还是非常重要并且出类拔萃
but that he was exceptional
做出这个决定后
And with this decision
上帝仿佛终于向他展颜微笑了
it seemed that the gods had at last begun to smile on him
萝拉?
Laura?
来了 爸爸
Coming, Papa
以前可没见过你啊
Haven't seen you here before
这是我在这儿的第一个收割季节
It's my first season
男女搭配 干活不累
Picking together is always more fun
听说你是大小通吃的人啊
They say you pick everything you find
蠢货! 跟你说了多少次了 别把花瓣胡掐乱塞
Idiot! How many times have I told you not to cram the blossoms in
跟填鸭似的
like you're stuffing a chicken?!
跟人家格雷诺耶学学
Watch how Grenouille does it
瞧他的手法 多灵巧
Look how skillfully he handles them
油脂离析法的要点就是让花朵慢慢衰谢
The whole art of enfleurage is to allow the flowers to die slowly
有如缓缓入眠
In their sleep, as it were
对待它们 就要像对待女士
Handle them as you would a lady
我说得没错吧 德鲁?
Wouldn't you agree with me, Druot?
如您所言 夫人
If you say so, Madame
你 去检查一下黄水仙花瓣
You, Check the jonquil blossoms
火候还没到
They need more time
我叫你去你就去!
Do what I say!
住手!
Stop it!
- 我没心情  - 真的?
- I'm not in the mood,  - Are you sure?
当然
Of course I'm sure
我说了
I said
不行!
no!
随你便
Suit yourself
路西安
Lucien?
帮我把梯子架上啊
Fetch me back the ladder
你自己架得了
Fetch it yourself
路西安?
Lucien?
路西安? !
Lucien?!
给阿尔努菲夫人送的晚香玉 她在吗?
Tuberoses for Madame Arnulfi, She here?
她忙着呢
She's busy
煮了它们真是浪费啊
Seems such a waste to boil them
还是怎么搞的来着
Or what ever you do with them
你们到底是怎么弄的?
So what do you do with them?
用动物油来煮
Warm them in animal fat
为什么?
What for?
这样油就吸收了香气
The fat soaks up their scent
然后呢?
Then what?
然后我等它凉却
Then I cool it to a pomade
过滤 接着…
and then I filter it before...
接着怎样?
Before what?
接着掺上酒精和其它精油 做成香水
Before I add in alcohol and other essences to make a perfume
什么都别碰
Don't touch anything
那里面是什么?
What's in there?
没什么 就是花
Nothing, Just flowers
- 我能看看吗?  - 不行
- Can I look?  - No
现在不行 我有工作要做 你该走了
Not now, I've got work to do, You must go now
别这样  让我看看
Come on, Let me look
不许碰
Don't touch
啊 我的晚香玉
Ah, my tuberoses
早啊 夫人
Morning, Madame
早
Morning
你怎么把罐子罩起来了?
Why have you covered the tank?
实验一下 夫人
It's an experiment, Madame
让花朵不受日光照射
To protect the blossoms from daylight
以便更好地保藏香气
To preserve the scent better
唔 你说是就是吧
Well, if you say so
跟我来
Come with me,
我给你主人记上账
I'll settle your master's account
更好地保藏香气 啊?
To preserve their scent better, you say?
我闻着没什么味道
I don't smell much
也是
No,
我的实验失败了
Then my experiment was a failure
你自己私底下胡混无所谓 该干活的钟点还得给我干活
Make sure it's your time you're wasting, not ours
多少钱?
How much must I pay
要和你在一起的话
to be with you?
看你想干嘛了
Depends what you want
那是什么玩意?
What's that stuff?
我在创造一种香水
I'm creating a perfume
请躺下
Lie down, please
怪恶心的
It feels horrible
这是动物油 用来吸收你的气味
It's only animal fat, To soak up your scent
创造一种香水 啊?
Creating a perfume, eh?
少装模作样了 承认吧 折腾这套古怪 你挺爽吧?
Come on, Admit it, You're getting some sort of bang out of this, aren't you?
对吧?
Arrest you?
我喜欢我的工作
I enjoy my work
手不要动
Hold your arm still
休想绑住我
Don't think you're gonna tie me up
请你伸手
Hold out your arm, please
有怪僻的家伙我倒也见过不少
I've come across some strange men in my time
你就...放松点
Just...relax
我的天 那是什么? !
Holy Mother, what's that?!
- 用来刮油的  - 你有毛病吧?
- Just for scraping off the fat,  - Are you mad?
我说了放松点
I said relax
别搞砸了
You'll ruin everything
你要是害怕起来 就会发臭 香水就变坏了
If you're frightened, you stink, Then your perfume will be spoiled
我受够了
I've had enough
出去!
Get out!
拿上你的钱
Here, take your money
涂得我浑身黏黏的
Basting me up in all this goo
你当我什么 圣诞节大鹅啊?
What do you think I am, a Christmas goose?
滚出去!
Get out of here!
快点吹灭了 免得玫瑰融了
Quickly, blow them out before the roses melt
- 玫瑰不会融的 爸爸  - 这些可是会的
- Roses can't melt, Papa,  - These ones can
我建议敬我们的贵客
Now I'd like to propose a toast
蒙特斯奇侯爵阁下一杯
to our guest of honor, His Excellency, the Marquis De Montesquieu
祝愿我们的生意继续欣欣向荣
May our trade continue to flourish
来 来
Here, here
感谢各位 也希望我有这个荣幸
I thank you all, and would ask of you the honor
第一个向您美丽的女儿说声恭喜
to be the first to offer my congratulations to your beautiful daughter
并向她送上一份我感情的见证
and present her with a small token of my affection
真美
It's beautiful
- 棒极了  - 好漂亮
- Splendid,  - It's beautiful
我受宠若惊 阁下
I'm overwhelmed, Your Grace
阁下?
Your Grace?
事到如今 跟我就不用这么客气了吧?
I had hoped that we would be on more familiar terms by now
不如来玩捉迷藏吧?
Let's have a game of hide and seek
噢 好
Oh, yes
但大家都要玩
But everyone must play,
男人找女人
Let the men catch the women,
好啊! 好啊!
Bravo! Bravo!
放我下来
Put me down
求你了?
Please?
这下无处可逃了吧
Now there's no escape
游戏结束了
Game's over, everybody
萝拉?
Laura?
该回来了
Time to go in now
萝拉?
Laura?
阿尔冰?
Albine?
佛朗斯法?
Franoise?
萝拉 你瞧见双胞胎姐妹了吗?
Laura, have you seen the twins?
没有 开始做游戏之后就没见着
No, not since the game started
阿尔冰 佛朗斯法?
Albine? Franoise?
雅克?
Jacques?
你们走这边
Take this way
你们两个跟我
You two with me
阁下?
Your Excellency?
这边走
Through here
阿尔冰! 佛朗斯法!
Albine! Franoise!
我跟那死小子说了十次了 叫他快点干完
I told that cretin ten times to get these ready!
别欺负小孩子
Don't keep picking on the boy
看我不宰了这没用的小杂种!
I'll kill him, the useless little sewer rat!
格雷诺耶!
Grenouille!
你在干嘛?
What are you doing?
怎么不去收拾萃取的…
Why aren't the enfleurage frames
什么事 师傅?
Yes, master?
麻烦你准备一下萃取用具好吗?
I mean, would you be good enough to prepare the enfleurage frames
让·巴蒂斯特?
Jean Baptiste?
好的 师傅
Certainly, master
嘿 看!
Hey, look!
天啊
Sweet
宵禁?
A curfew?!
你疯了吗?
Are you mad?!
茉莉只能在破晓前采摘 我们都清楚
Jasmine can only be picked before dawn, We all know that
这样我们的生意就毁了 包括你的
This could mean the ruin of our trade, Yours
还有你的 你的
And yours and yours
下次轮到你女儿头上怎么办?
Supposing it's your daughter next time
宵禁是必要的 但我们也必须抓住那家伙
Of course a curfew is necessary, but we also have to catch this man
这才能搞清楚他的想法
and the only way to do that is to understand how he thinks
想要什么
what he wants
我想这很明显
I should have thought that was obvious
想想看吧!
Use your imagination
那我告诉你 除了那个妓女
And if I were to tell you that all except the prostitute
其余女孩遇害时 贞洁都不曾遭人点染
went to their graves with their chastity intact?
你怎么知道的?
How would you know?
验尸官做了检查 她们都还是处女之身
The coroner had each girl examined, They were all found to be virgins
如果没有下次了呢?
Supposing there isn't a next time?
要是贸然宵禁 我们都会白白破产
If we introduce a curfew we may all go bankrupt for nothing
难道我们就眼睁睁地等着? 等他杀掉六个?
So we wait until he's killed, what? Six?
七个? 八个?
Seven? Eight?
上帝宽恕 是波林
Lord save us, It's Pauline
- 宵禁了! 回家!  - 呆在家里
- Curfew! Go back to your homes!  - Stay inside
宵禁了 回家去
It's a curfew, Back inside
各位先生!
Gentlemen!
我们应该意识到本地警方对此无能为力
We have to face the fact that our police are helpless in this matter
我建议我们应该请求巴黎警方援助
I suggest that we ask for support from Paris
巴黎人也不见得有多厉害
Paris won't be smarter than we are
我们必须逮捕普罗旺斯的所有吉普赛人和乞丐
We must arrest every Gypsy in Provence! And every beggar!
还有没有妻室的男人
And every man without a wife and family!
听着
Listen
我们要置身处地 推测他的想法
We have to put ourselves inside the mind of this man
每一个受害人都有其特别的美
Each of his victims had an especial beauty
他既然没有侵犯他们
We know he doesn't want their virginity
那吸引他的应该是这美丽本身
so it seems to me that it's their beauty itself that he wants
仿佛他在收集什么似的
It's almost as if he's trying to gather something
他简直有着收藏家的野心
As if his ambitions are those of a collector
收藏家? 收藏什么?
A collector? Of what?
她们的头发?
Their hair?
滚出去 滚出我的店!
Get out! Get out of my store!
你个人渣!
You murdering scum!
无论是什么
Whatever it is
在他完成全套藏品之前恐怕是不会罢手的了
I fear he won't stop killing until his collection is complete
拿着 下一个 快点 对了
There you are, Next, Quick as you can, Right
还有你
You, too
先生
Monsieur
这人 这人是恶魔
This man, this man is a demon
是人力不能抵御的幽灵
A phantom who cannot be fought by human means
我坚决提议 去找主教驱逐这个妖人!
Now, I insist that we call upon our bishop to excommunicate him!
那能有什么用?
What good would that do?
你难道不相信我们教堂的圣灵吗?
Have you no faith in the power of our Holy Mother Church?
这不是信不信的问题!
This is not a matter of faith
凶手逍遥法外
There's a murderer out there
我们要抓住他 得靠上帝赐予我们的头脑
and we must catch him by using our God. Given wits!
依我看 如果不向教会求助
I say until we submit to Mother Church
凶手是不会善罢甘休的
these killings will not cease
格拉斯的公民们
Citizens of Grasse
我们在此宣布这杀手乃是恶魔
we hereby declare that this murderer, this demon in our midst
我们要将其驱逐出境!
has incurred the sentence of excommunication
这怪兽的恶爪掳走了我们的女儿
Not only has this depraved monster robbed us of our daughters
我们城邦年轻美丽的花朵
the young and fair blossom of this city
他蓄意凶残的行径
and by his wanton acts
损伤了我们的生意 我们的营生 而且
has brought our trade, our livelihood, nay
我们的生存被逼到了无尽的黑暗边缘
our very existence to the brink of eternal darkness
由此我们判决
We therefore declare
这卑劣的毒蛇
that this vile viper
可耻的脓疮
this ignominious carbuncle
我们身边的恶魔
this execrable evil in our midst
我们圣洁的教区就此向其施以严正的诅咒
shall henceforth be solemnly banned from our holy presence
以圣母的名义
rejected from the communion of Holy Mother Church
从我们身边驱除这个撒旦的门徒
as a disciple of Satan
灵魂的杀手
slayer of souls
让路! 让路!
Stand clear! Stand clear!
这是对我们信仰的侮辱
An infected limb
对圣灵的无视
an outsider of the faith
这魔鬼的随从 恶毒的巫师
a necromancer, a diabolist, a sorcerer
可鄙的异教徒
and a damned heretic
神啊 请赐予您的仁慈
Oh, God, in Thy most merciful spirit
让他五雷轰顶
bring down thunderbolts upon his head
让恶魔化为灰烬吧
and may the Devil make soup of his bones
阿门!
Amen!
主教大人! 主教大人!
My Lord! My Lord!
真是神迹啊! 他被抓住了!
It's a miracle! He's been caught!
他被抓住了!
He's been caught!
主教大人 魔鬼已经被抓住了
My Lord, the fiend has been caught
在格勒诺布尔
In the city of Grenoble
他供认不讳!
He's confessed to everything!
供认不讳!
啊 哈利路亚! 哈利路亚!
Oh, hallelujah, Hallelujah!
赞美主啊!
Praise be to God!
感谢您倾听我们的祈祷并给予了回答
And we thank Him for listening to our prayers and answering them
阿门!
Amen!
你读一读这报告就知道了不可能是这个人
Just read the report, This cannot possibly be the same man
他全招认了 包括在格拉斯的凶杀案
He confessed to everything, Including the murders in Grasse
没错 可那是在酷刑伺候之下
Yes, Under to rture
你看这里
Look, Here
他承认他扼死了被害者们扯下她们的头发
He admits to strangling his victims, pulling out their hair
并强暴了她们
and ravaging them
格拉斯的少女们都是脑后一击致命
The girls of Grasse were killed by a single blow to the back of their heads
头发被仔细剪干净 也不曾被人侵犯
their hair was carefully cropped, and not one of them was violated
安托万
Antoine
大家都很高兴事情已经结束了
we're all happy it's over
就此罢手吧!
Let it go!
爸爸 出什么事了?
Papa, what's the matter?
我们回家 马上!
We're going home, Now!
但为什么? 我玩得正高兴呢
But why? I'm enjoying myself
不许顶撞 萝拉!
Don't argue with me, Laura
住手! 我要…
Stop it! I'm going...
萝拉!
Laura!
别挡道!
Out of my way!
萝拉!
Laura!
爸爸!
Papa!
真对不起
I'm so sorry
你一定觉得我很愚蠢
I know you must think me a very foolish man
但请谅解
but try to understand
你是我仅有的一切了
you're all I have left
你不需要解释 爸爸
You don't need to explain, Papa
如果你有什么三长两短
If anything were to happen to you
我明白 但你不用老这么担心我啊
I know, But you must stop worrying about me all the time
做个好梦 宝贝
Sweet dreams, my love
做个好梦 爸爸
Sweet dreams, Papa
萝拉!
Laura!
爸爸 出什么事了?
Papa, what's the matter?
你开窗了吗?
Did you open the window?
没有 为什么?
No, Why?
立刻把这封信送去给蒙特斯奇侯爵
Have this letter dispatched to the Marquis de Montesquieu immediately
玛丽 快点!
Marie? Quickly!
停下!
Steady!
你们继续向北 进山
Stay on the road north into the mountains
里希先生走了
Did Monsieur Richis leave?
对
He did
走的哪条路?
Which way?
北边
North
你确定不是走的南面吗?
You sure it wasn't south?
我亲眼看见的
I saw them with my own eyes
你为什么想知道?
Why do you want to know?
我说了是北边!
I said north!
北边!
North!
格雷诺耶?
Grenouille?
格雷诺耶? !
Grenouille?!
天哪!
Good God!
下午好 先生
Good afternoon, Monsieur
下午好 还有别人住在这里吗?
Good afternoon, Do you have anyone else staying here?
没有 先生
No, Monsieur
那今晚我包下了
Then I would like to take all your rooms for the night
非常荣幸 先生
It will be our pleasure, Monsieur
明天清早 我们想乘渡船到圣奥诺拉
And tomorrow, at first light, we wish to be ferried to the Ile de Lrin
那里废弃了 只有些修道士…
It's deserted except for a few monks...
我知道
I'm aware of that
明白 先生
Very well, Monsieur
这是我们最好的房间 小姐
Our finest room, Mademoiselle
你看这海景
With a superb view of the sea
等等
One moment
很好
Very well
有没有邻着的房间?
Do you have a room next to this one?
有 但相比之下 风景就远不如…
Yes, but the view cannot be compared...
我对风景没兴趣
I have no interest in the view
爸爸 能告诉我出了什么事吗?
Papa, will you please tell me now what's happening?
你整天都一言不发
You haven't said a word all day
为什么这么神秘?
Why all this secrecy?
昨晚我梦见你死了
Last night I dreamt you were dead
和其它姑娘一样 被谋杀了
Murdered, Like all the other girls
实话说 我确信凶手还未曾落网
And the truth is, I'm convinced that the killer is still here somewhere
每个被害者都很年轻美丽
All of his victims were young and beautiful
而还有谁能比你更美呢 萝拉?
and who is there more beautiful than you, Laura?
不论他有什么疯狂的阴谋 没有得到你 他一定誓不罢休
Whatever his insane scheme, it will surely be incomplete without you
我已经给蒙特斯奇侯爵回了信
I've written to the Marquis,
代你应允了他的求婚
accepting his proposal of marriage on your behalf
并要求婚礼尽快举行
and requesting that it take place as soon as possible
在此之前 你得待在修道院以确保安全
Until then, you stay in the safety of the monastery
这一切 只因为你做了一个恶梦?
And all this, because you had a bad dream?
我已经决定了
I've made my decision,
但我甚至还不知道我爱不爱他!
But I don't know whether I even love him
形势所迫 不容我们选择
I'm afraid the circumstances leave us no choice
- 爸爸  - 就这么定了 萝拉
- Papa,  - It's all arranged, Laura
站住!
On your feet!
把手举起来!
Hands in the air!
你为什么要杀我女儿?
Why did you kill my daughter?
为什么?
Why?
我需要她
I needed her
你为什么要杀我女儿?
Why did you kill my daughter?
我只是...
I just...
需要她
needed her
好吧
Very well
可你给我记住
But remember this
我会看着你...
I'll be looking at you...
被钉到木十字架上
when you're laid on the cross
等十二杖棍刑 击碎了你的四肢
and the twelve blows are crashing down on your limbs
等到围观的众人终于厌倦了你痛苦的叫喊 四散归去
And when the crowd has finally tired of your screams and wandered home
我会踏过你的血泊
I will climb up through your blood
在你身边坐下
and sit beside you
凝视进你的双眼
I will look deep into your eyes
我的眼神将一点一滴的
and, drop by drop
将对你的憎恨慢慢灌入
I will trickle my disgust into them
有如灼热的硫酸
like burning acid
直至...
until...
...最终...
...finally...
...你的死亡
...you perish
你觉得他们会怎么处置他?
What do you think they'll do to him?
好像是要用铁棍敲碎他所有的骨头
Apparently they're gonna break every bone in his body with an iron bar
肮脏的家伙!
Filthy piece of bile
蠢货!
Fathead!
看 他来了
Look, there he comes
把犯人的锁链解开
Unchain the prisoner
行了!
That's enough!
带他去刑场
Let him be brought to the scaffold
那是什么
What's that?
他来了吗? 那是什么?
Is he coming? What is it?
这人是无辜的!
This man is innocent!
不是他干的 不可能!
He didn't do it, It's impossible
他是无辜的!
He's innocent!
天使!
An angel!
这不是凡人!
This is no man!
这是天使!
This is an angel!
格雷诺耶!
Grenouille!
你休想骗过我!
You can't fool me!
原谅我
Forgive me
我的儿子
my son
格拉斯人仿佛宿醉醒来 头痛如裂
The people of Grasse awoke to a terrible hangover
对多数人而言 此次经历实在骇人听闻 难以解释
For many of them, the experience was so ghastly, so completely inexplicable
且与他们所持的道德观念背道而驰
and incompatible with their morals
于是 事后他们干脆彻底抹除了这段记忆
that they literally erased it from their memories
镇上的参议会下午商讨决定
The town council was in session by the afternoon
命令警察局
and an order was passed to the police lieutenant
立即重新开展调查
to immediately begin fresh investigations into the murders
翌日 多米尼克·德鲁就被逮捕了
The following day, Dominique Drouth was arrested since it was in his backyard
因为被害者的衣服和头发终归都是在他的后院找到的
that the clothes and hair of all the victims had been found
十四个小时的严刑拷打之后,他招认了一切
After 14 hours of torture, Drouth confessed to everything
本案件就此了结
With that, the case was closed
此时 格雷诺耶已经在返回巴黎的半路上了
By then, Grenouille was already halfway back to Paris
只要他愿意 他手上剩下的香水 足以征服整个世界
He still had enough perfume left to enslave the whole world if he so chose
他可以走到凡尔赛去让国王亲吻他的脚
He could walk to Versailles and have the King kiss his feet
他可以给教皇写封香水信宣布自己是新的救世主
He could write the Pope a perfumed letter and reveal himself as the new Messiah
只要他愿意 他可以随心所欲
He could do all this and more if he wanted to
他手中掌握的这种威力比金钱 恐惧 或死亡更强大
He possessed a power stronger than the power of money, or terror, or death
可以激发人类的爱慕之心 所向披靡
the invincible power to command the love of mankind
只有一件事是香水做不到的
There was only one thing the perfume could not do
它无法使他如常人一般爱...
It could not turn him into a person who could love...
...与被爱
...and be loved like everyone else
那就都见鬼去吧 他想
So, to hell with it, he thought
这世界 这香水和他自己都见鬼去吧
To hell with the world, With the perfume, With himself
在一七六六年六月二十五日约晚上十一点
On the 25th of June, 1766, around 11 o'clock at night
格雷诺耶通过奥尔良港口回到巴黎
Grenouille entered the city through the Port d'Orlans
有如一个梦游者
and like a sleepwalker
他的嗅觉记忆将他带回了出生的地方
his olfactory memories drew him back to the place where he was born
天使啊!
An angel
我爱你!
I love you!
没过多久 让·巴蒂斯特格雷诺耶
Within no time, Jean Baptiste Grenouille
就从世间消失了
had disappeared from the face of the earth
事后 他们满心都是圣洁的幸福光辉
When they had finished, they felt a virginal glow of happiness
有生以来第一次
For the first time in their lives
他们觉得自己所作所为
they believed they have done something
乃是源自内心纯粹的爱
purely out of love
那里!
Over here!
看!
Look!
一件夹克
A jacket
拿回家去吧
Let's take them all home
给你穿好了
You can wear them